Hello, welcome to my True Criminelle podcast.
My name is Marianne Elle and
you are very, very welcome.
Now, when we think about keeping our homes safe,
we picture locked doors, security cameras
and watching out for strangers.
But danger doesn't always come from the outside.
Sometimes it walks through the
front door because we invited it in.
We trust licensed professionals.
People hired to fix our homes,
improve them, make them safer.
They're the last people we expect
to bring harm across our threshold.
But in the autumn of 2019, in the quiet community
of Fleming Island in Florida,
that is exactly what happened to a
65-year-old widow, Susan Mouldin.
She trusted a contractor named Corey Binderim to
put right the work she paid for.
Instead, a simple home
renovation dispute spiralled into tragedy.
This is the case of Susan Mouldin, a woman who
stood her ground against a dishonest contractor
and paid for it with her life.
[Music]
So Susan Elizabeth Mouldin was a 65-year-old
British native who had immigrated to the United
States decades earlier and built a fulfilling
life for herself in Fleming Island, Florida.
Following the passing of her husband John in
2006, Susan was left as a
widow living on her own.
But she was fiercely independent and threw
herself into her hobbies,
whether she was tending to her beloved garden or
busy with her weekly knitting circle.
Susan didn't have any children or family locally,
but she was far from isolated.
One of the clubs she belonged
to was the local British club,
which was a unique group originally founded
after World War II for British women
who had moved to the US after
marrying American servicemen.
She had a really large
tight-knit group of friends,
many of them from this British club.
And she was just the kind of person
who kept her calendar
constantly full with social events.
Susan loved her home. She loved to host and
entertain her tight-knit circle of friends.
Her friends, I guess, were like
the family that she didn't have.
For Susan, her house on Harbor Town Drive wasn't
just a place that she lived.
It was her sanctuary and she
took immense pride in her home.
So when in 2018 she decided it was finally time
to update her guest bathroom,
it wasn't just about maintenance.
Obviously that was important, but it was about
making her home perfect for the
people she loved to welcome inside.
So to get the job done
right, she hired a professional.
That professional was
44-year-old Corey Binderim.
So on paper, Corey Binderim seemed like a safe
bet. He had the credentials, plus he already had
Susan's trust having previously completed a small
job in her kitchen. So she kind of knew him.
And because he had presented himself as capable
and professional in the past,
she didn't hesitate to hire him again for her
guest bathroom, which was a much bigger job.
But she trusted him and made multiple payments
totaling $12,000 to cover the work.
In early 2019, Binderim arrived at Susan's house
and did the easy part of the job the
demolition. I mean, I could
have probably done that to be fair.
Now he tore out her old bathroom, removing the
tiling, the flooring, the walls and he
left her with a gutted, unusable shell of a room,
which is absolutely fine, except the
progress stopped.
Binderim stopped showing up to do the work,
leaving Susan's bathroom
looking like a construction zone.
He had pulled everything out and that was it.
He just left her with this mess.
So as you can imagine, poor Susan was desperate
for the work to be completed.
I mean, she had paid him $12,000,
so she had every right to
demand that the work be done.
But whenever she called him or texted him,
she was met with a barrage of excuses.
He would tell her things like there was a delay
in shipping the materials.
His equipment was stolen.
He fell out of his truck and had
to go to the hospital to get an MRI.
There was a family emergency or he had to pick up
his children from school.
I mean, there's only so many
excuses one person can take.
Now Susan was meticulously organised and when I
say meticulously almost compulsively and
that was just her, she really was organised, she
wrote everything down. She kept records
of everything.
Every single excuse Binderim
had given her, she wrote it down.
The time, the date, what the excuse was.
For eight months she watched the excuses grow.
For eight months she
lived with a ruined bathroom.
And this wasn't just her being petty.
Her being able to socialise in
her own home was who she was.
So it wasn't just the bathroom wasn't done.
A part of her life was on hold as well.
She really wanted to give
Binderim the benefit of the doubt.
But as the excuses piled up,
so did the realisation
that she was being scammed.
(upbeat music)
So there was another problem.
It wasn't just that Binderim
hadn't completed the bathroom.
Susan also felt intimidated by him.
She told one of her close friends, Phyllis Yates,
that she was afraid of being alone with him.
Susan told Phyllis about an unsettling incident
where Binderim turned up at Susan's home
and inappropriately started complimenting
her physical appearance.
In other words, he was kinda coming onto her.
You know, she's a widow in her 60s,
he was a married man in his 40s,
and she was creeped out and uncomfortable.
But the thing was, this interaction was loaded
with an ulterior motive.
Because Binderim then went on to ask her
for a personal loan.
So basically, he was trying
to take advantage of Susan.
You know, he has access to her home.
He knows she lives alone.
He knows that, you know, she has some money.
He knows she's an older lady,
potentially a bit more vulnerable.
Now Susan flatly refused, good on her.
She was a strong lady and
not going to be walked over.
She had already paid him a massive deposit
for a bathroom he hadn't built.
And she wasn't about to give him more money.
She knew she was never going to see again.
In fact, Susan had had enough,
and absolute enough of this man.
She had spent the last few months getting more
and more frustrated,
constantly complaining to her friends
about her incompetent contractor.
She had decided she was going to get her money
back and find another contractor to do the work.
On Wednesday the 23rd of October 2019, at around
about half past seven in the morning,
Binderim called Susan with yet another excuse.
He said he was tied up in court and could no
longer make their scheduled meeting, which
actually might well have been true because he did
have a number of court appearances.
I don't know whether he had one on that morning
or not, but either way, he wasn't turning
up to do the work again.
And it was the final straw.
Susan officially confronted him and demanded her
$12,000 back and laid down a strict ultimatum.
She said if Binderim didn't show up with her
money that very day, she was going to
hire a lawyer and go straight to
the police to file fraud charges.
She had evidence of all the excuses.
She was a smart lady.
She kept records of everything.
Now, that same day, later
on around about lunchtime,
she met with her friend Phyllis.
It was one of their regular lunch
dates they had every single Wednesday.
You know, they were really, really close friends.
Now, Susan spent this meal just venting about the
situation, explaining to Phyllis she had fired
Binderim and given him a
final deadline to pay up.
She was not going to take any more of his crap.
Now, I think Phyllis was relieved that her friend
was standing her ground,
but she was also concerned about
the situation and wary of Binderim,
and she was right to be, because when Binderim
received Susan's ultimatum,
he knew that Susan wasn't messing around,
and he was kind of panicked a bit by her threat
to go to the authorities.
The last thing that Binderim
wanted was the police involved,
but he didn't actually
have the money to give her.
So he scrambled to buy himself a
bit more time, a few more hours,
and he promised Susan that he would hand-deliver
a refund check to her home
first thing the next morning.
So when Susan went to bed that Wednesday night,
she was hopeful that the next day, which was
going to be Thursday the 24th of October,
She was hopeful that her dishonest contractor
would pay his debts, and she
could finally move on with her life.
She had no way of knowing that Binderim had no
intention of handing over her cheque,
or that he had already planned her murder.
So who was Corey Binderim?
He was a local Clay County resident.
He had a large network of friends in the area.
To the outside world, Corey Binderim appeared to
be an ordinary family man.
They always just appear ordinary.
He had a successful business.
He was living in an affluent area with his wife,
Cassidy, and their two daughters.
However, behind Binderim's
personal and professional exterior
was a man whose life was in a state of collapse.
Binderim was struggling with substance abuse.
He had an incredibly expensive cocaine addiction
and he was drowning in debt.
The truth was his business was
completely running out of money.
Other clients were already suing him for walking
away from their jobs and taking their cash
with him, which is why I was thinking when he
said he was in court, he might well have
been because other clients were suing him.
And so basically he became trapped in this
vicious cycle to keep angry
clients from calling the police.
He would take upfront deposits from new clients
and immediately use that fresh cash to either pay
older clients who were threatening him
or to fund his heavy drug habit.
So when Susan handed him that $12,000 check,
the money didn't go towards
new tiles and modern fixtures
or plumbing supplies.
It was instantly swallowed up
by Binderim's mounting debts
and substance abuse problem.
So Susan's ultimatum was a
massive threat to his reputation.
If Susan went to the police, he knew an
investigation into his
business would expose his drug use,
his empty bank account and his fraudulent
business practices to the world.
It would mean the end of his
career and possibly prison time.
Furthermore, the exposure
would destroy his family.
This wasn't his first
time dealing with addiction.
His wife Cassidy had actually discovered his
struggles at least 10 years earlier.
But back then, she had given him a strict choice.
She said get treatment and stay clean, or she
would leave him and take their daughters.
So for a decade, Cassidy
believed he had stayed sober.
She had no idea that he was actively using again.
And Binderim could not risk
her finding out the truth now.
Susan Mouldin's ultimatum threatened everything.
So he began taking the first steps
of a dark premeditated plan
to make his problem disappear for good.
So the following day was
Thursday, the 24th of October.
Phyllis tried to call Susan several times,
but the calls went straight to voicemail.
Phyllis was deeply concerned.
It was totally uncharacteristic
for Susan to ignore her friends' calls.
However, at the same time,
after speaking to Susan at
their lunch the previous day,
Phyllis knew that Susan was expecting Binderim
to deliver her refund money that morning.
And so Phyllis thought
that once Susan had the money,
that would mean she could find another contractor
to complete the bathroom.
And so Phyllis reasoned that
maybe she was just preoccupied,
you know, with stuff,
trying to find other contractors to do the work.
However, by the next day, by Friday 25th October,
Phyllis was beginning to panic.
At around about 11am, she drove
to Susan's house to check on her.
From the outside,
everything looked deceptively normal.
Pumpkins were sat on the front porch
in anticipation of Halloween.
Peering through the garage window,
Phyllis could see Susan's car
parked inside the garage still
so she believed she hadn't gone anywhere.
Her car was still there.
It's possible she could have gone with somebody
but it wouldn't have been like Susan to do that.
She would have told her
friends what she was doing.
Phyllis knocked loudly on the front door
but there was no response.
Phyllis walked around to the back of the property
and again, there was nothing.
Now Phyllis had to return to work, but obviously
she hadn't found Susan and
was so so worried about her.
So she called her husband Dan and told him
that she still couldn't find Susan.
She had a feeling that
something was terribly wrong,
you know, those intuitive
gut feelings that you get
that you shouldn't ever ignore.
So she asked her husband Dan
to go around with a spare key
that Susan had given them for emergencies.
And later that afternoon,
Dan drove to Susan's house.
As he approached the front door,
he noticed a couple of business cards
that had been wedged in the doorframe.
These were the contractor cards
because she had made
appointments with new contractors
and clearly she hadn't opened the door to them.
Dan slid the spare key
into the lock and turned it,
but only a crack because it was restricted
by the security chain or bolt
or whatever locked it from the inside.
So the door didn't open fully.
So one would assume if the internal locks were on
that Susan must be inside the house.
Now Dan called and called and, you know, hollered
through the door and knocked,
but she still didn't come.
So Dan had to reach his arm through the narrow
gap and slide off the chain
before he could finally step inside.
Now, I know you shouldn't be able to do that,
but it was actually Dan who had fixed the bolt or
the chain to the inside himself.
And he had done it wrong.
He'd put it on the wrong way round or something.
So he knew it was faulty, but no one else other
than him and Susan, obviously,
knew that this chain was faulty.
But because he knew it was faulty, he was able to
slide his hand in and open the door.
Once inside, Dan was met with the sound of the
television playing in the next room.
Now Susan never left her TV
on when she was going out.
Dan said that even if she was going to the
garden, she would turn it off.
Dan also noticed that a light
had been left on in the kitchen.
And again, it was a light
that he knew she didn't use.
Besides, it was the middle of the afternoon, so
it made no sense why the light would be on.
Dan walked through the house
repeatedly, calling out Susan's name.
But there was no answer.
So he contacted his wife and the Clay County
Sheriff's office to report Susan missing.
When the police turned up to do the initial
welfare check, it was difficult to tell whether
a crime had been committed at first glance. There
were no signs of forced entry, there
were no windows broken, the bolt was still on
from inside as we know. If Susan had opened
the door to someone, it
was likely someone she knew.
Susan kept her home as meticulously clean and
tidy as her filing system.
You know, she really was an organised lady. So
looking at the house, it was pretty neat.
But looking past that neatness at the smaller
details were when the red flags emerged.
The little things that people knew about Susan,
they knew that it just wasn't right.
In the hallway, a picture frame hangs slightly
skewed at a slight angle.
Decorative figurines had
been knocked out of place.
In the master bedroom, Susan's normally neat and
tidy bed sat completely unmade.
A rug next to the bed was visibly out of
position. Her trainers were
still sitting on the bedroom
floor. I assume just like the car, it meant that
she probably hadn't walked somewhere
without putting her shoes on.
In the master bathroom sink, a damp cloth sat in
a basin half full of water.
It initially appeared as though Susan's laptop
and mobile phone were missing,
but it was in Susan's home office that there was
something really quite strange.
As I said, she had this filing
system and she had a filing cabinet,
which makes sense, you
know, she really was organised.
Apparently she kept absolutely everything, even
appliance manuals, things like that.
But this filing cabinet had a red folder,
labelled Binderim Remodelling.
Inside the folder, the contents were missing.
Now knowing Susan, that
folder would not have been empty.
This bathroom saga had been going on for months.
There wouldn't be nothing in that folder.
But also, what a bloody idiot.
Imagine taking the contents but
not the folder with your name on.
I mean, I'm assuming in his head
he's thinking it must just look normal.
It might have looked less normal
if the folder wasn't there at all,
but leave something in it.
I mean, I guess he just took everything in a
hurry, but blinkin' heck, what an idiot.
Anyway, there are little
signs that things aren't right.
She also had a doctor's appointment scheduled
that day, which she didn't turn up for.
And Susan wouldn't have not turned up, or at
least not told them that she wasn't turning up.
Plus she'd missed other appointments with
contractors, as we know,
because the cards were in the door.
She just wouldn't have not turned up to things.
She wasn't that kind of woman,
it just wasn't her character.
So where the hell was she?
Over the coming days, there would be no activity
on her credit cards, no answer to calls or
text on her mobile phone, no contact with her
closest friends, nothing.
Police considered the possibility that Susan had
flown back to England, but when they checked
her passport, there was no record of a flight.
Plus, when they interviewed her friends, it was
clear Susan was a creature of habit and
spoke to people regularly.
She would never have gone on a
trip without telling anybody first.
But the most vital piece of information the
police learned from Susan's friends
was the intense dispute that she
was having with a local contractor.
And within days, the police had pulled
surveillance videos from
neighbouring ring doorbells
as well as from school bus
cameras that went down Susan's street.
And when they saw a white pickup truck backed up
to the garage of Susan's home on
the morning of her disappearance,
they were immediately concerned.
Because the truck belonged to the same local
contractor that all of
Susan's friends had told them about,
Corey Binderim.
[Music]
So when officers first contacted Binderim, he
behaved like a completely
innocent cooperative businessman.
He willingly agreed to speak with them and
projected an air of calm professionalism.
Now over the course of his interviews he did get
flustered and change his story a few times
but overall he painted a picture of Susan being
the problem. Not him but Susan.
He claimed he had been stuck on her bathroom
remodel for eight months because she was a
difficult, indecisive client who constantly
changed her mind about tiles and fixtures
i.e. what she wanted.
Ultimately he thought it was easier to just
refund her and for them
to go their separate ways.
Binderim claimed that on
the morning she disappeared.
He had arrived at her house
at around 8am that morning
just to make peace, complete some
paperwork and end their contract.
He even showed investigators a carbon copy of a
refund check to prove it.
He was adamant he had gone around, ended their
contract and refunded Susan's money.
But the carbon copy of the cheque that he showed
the police was written for just $1,200.
Not $12,000, $1,200.
Falsely claiming that that was the
total amount she had ever paid him.
He said that once he'd paid her, he collected his
remaining plumbing tools from her guest
bathroom, loaded them into his truck and left,
leaving a perfectly alive Susan behind.
It seemed like a simple and clean alibi.
But investigators were deeply suspicious,
especially when they pulled his financial
records and discovered that his business accounts
were practically empty holding less than $100.
So he had absolutely no way of covering even the
$1200 payment he claimed he made.
So far, Binderim was the only one with any
financial motive to harm Susan.
She had no family and her will actually named
three charities as her beneficiaries,
meaning there was nobody that
stood to gain from her death.
So the only conflict in
her life was Corey Binderim.
You know you lied to me, right? When we called on
Tuesday about what you said,
all you owed her was $1,294 and 54 cents.
And that's the carbon check.
You showed me dated for 10/24.
That's the check that I wrote her to reimburse.
You owed her $12,000 and I have all the checks
that she wrote out to you.
There's three of them.
Along with her meticulous
detailed list of the money that she gave.
Right.
Why would you lie about that? Because 1,200 is a
big difference than 12,000.
Right. No, 1,200.
So you're still adamant, even though I'm telling
you I've got the checks
that she gave you $12,000,
you're saying that she was okay with that
Thursday when y'all talked.
Yeah.
She's like, "All right, I'm good. I'll let you do
the work." Even though there's tons of people
were saying she had enough, she was done, you
were either going to give her her
cash or cashier's check or she
was going to sue you and report you.
Have a great weekend now.
Alright, I'm sorry to mess it up for you.
So basically, they're suspicious and officers and
forensic teams returned to Susan's home
to do a thorough search of her home.
When one of the officers noticed a small drop of
blood on the floor, forensic teams sprayed
the floors and walls with luminol.
The chemical reaction was immediate with blood
spatter discovered on the living room lamp
shade.
There were also signs of blood spots on the floor
in the living room and the garage.
Evidence of blood clean up was also found on the
floor in front of the kitchen sink.
Someone had spilt blood in Susan's home and
someone had gone to great lengths to clean it up.
It was glaringly obvious to investigators that a
violent struggle had taken place
and this was no longer a
missing person investigation.
Susan had not left that house voluntarily.
As investigators continued looking at Cory
Binderim, it didn't take long for his story
to completely fall apart.
They obtained a search warrant for his mobile
phone records and discovered that he had deleted
any evidence of communication between him and
Susan around the time of her disappearance.
Furthermore, they established he had completely
omitted some rather crucial timeline details
about his whereabouts on the
day of Susan's disappearance.
Cellular tower pings placed his phone in the area
of the Home Depot in Fleming Island at
around about seven o'clock in the morning, before
he had even arrived at Susan's home.
Detectives went to that Home Depot
and pulled the store's CCTV footage.
There, on camera, they saw Binderim buying two
60-pound bags of concrete and a roll of
heavy-duty demolition bags.
Now, he was in construction, to be fair.
It's not that unusual.
But why didn't he tell them?
Additionally, an examination of his phone showed
he had the Life360 tracking app installed.
Now this was because of his
previous substance abuse issues.
Binderim had agreed with his wife Cassidy
to keep the tracking app on his phone
so she could monitor his whereabouts.
However, investigators
noticed he had turned the app off
for around about an hour at 8.45 on the morning
of Susan's disappearance.
Why the hell would you
turn your tracking app off?
He had something to hide.
So where was he during that hour?
Using cellular tower activity, investigators
delved deeper and found that during the time
he had turned his tracking app off, he had
visited the local landfill where he spent
a few minutes dumping
something at the trash site.
So Home Depot where he buys concrete, Susan's
home where he supposedly refunds her and then
the dump site.
It's not suspicious at all, at
least it wouldn't be if he'd told them.
But again, you know, he's a contractor.
Let's give him the benefit
of the doubt, if we have to.
Now, he admitted to
retrieving his tools from Susan's home.
So the investigators then turned their attention
to Binderim's storage unit.
They obtained surveillance footage of him
entering the facility at around about 9.50am.
But there was no video of what he was actually
unloading into the unit.
So investigators brought in cadaver dogs to the
unit and the dog gave a positive alert
for human decomposition on the tool bag he had
removed from Susan's home.
I think my benefit of the
doubt has gone out of the window.
So he's guilty as hell, but
there's the slight matter of proving it.
Because don't forget, they
still don't know where Susan is.
Detectives knew Binderim was hiding something and
a few days later they headed to his home
with a warrant to seize his truck.
As his truck was being towed away, the detectives
chatting to him outside noticed he had a fresh
scratch on his arm.
Binderim claimed it was from working in
construction, but detectives
documented its significance
anyway.
Now throughout their chat whilst his car is being
towed away, Binderim was adamant.
He had left Susan alive on the 24th and he had no
idea what happened to her.
He felt that the police were targeting him
specifically because of his prior criminal
record.
This man had a prior criminal record.
When Binderim was 17 years old, he had
participated in a robbery
which involved a shooting and
was convicted of aggravated battery with a
firearm and sentenced to a minimum of three
years in prison and 10 years probation.
The police didn't have the
tunnel vision that he claimed.
Binderim's prior conviction showed them
exactly what kind of man he was.
He was a man capable of violence.
And when they got the news a little later
that Binderim had gone on the run,
they knew that their vision was spot on.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
So just four days after
his vehicle had been seized,
Binderim's wife contacted the police
and said he had left town.
She had absolutely no idea where he was.
Now Binderim obviously knew investigators
weren't buying his story.
And he could feel the net tightening.
But instead of facing the
music, Binderim chose to run.
But fleeing the state requires money, something
we know he doesn't have.
So what does he do?
He steals it.
Of course he does.
He went to another client's home in Jacksonville
and stole a cheque worth $5,000.
He basically forged the guy's
signature and then cashed this cheque in.
So armed with the stolen cash, Binderim dumped
his mobile phone, purchased a burner phone
and fled Florida.
He showed a complete lack of remorse, not only
for his clients but his family as well.
He had two daughters, don't forget.
In fact it was the night of his daughter's
birthday party I believe.
Binderim just put himself first.
He drove thousands of miles across
the country and fled to Colorado.
Now his wife Cassidy helped the investigators and
provided them with the numbers of the
burner phones that Binderim was using.
You know looking at her police interviews she had
absolutely no idea about any of this
and was pretty disgusted with him.
So she basically helped the investigators and in
fact this whole thing does lead to
them getting a divorce.
By early December, knowing his face was on wanted
posters and it's difficult to run
without surveillance catching up to you
eventually, the pressure
was just becoming too much for
Binderim and he turned himself in.
On the 3rd December 2019, he was arrested and
arraigned in the Duval County Jail.
But he only turned
himself in on the fraud charges,
i.e. stealing the cheque.
And so that was what he was charged with.
He was still firmly denying,
having anything to do with
the disappearance of Susan.
(upbeat music)
So Corey is now locked up.
He's in custody on unrelated fraud charges.
So he was off the street, but for how long?
You know, they could only
keep him behind bars for so long
without charging him for Susan's murder.
But they had a problem
because without Susan's body,
proving a homicide in
court is incredibly difficult.
Plus rather more
importantly, you know, her loved ones
are suffering here, they have no closure.
Without a body, there's always hope, you know?
So people clung on to that hope.
And that leaves people in limbo.
They can't grieve, they can't move on.
And so they're kind of in
this limbo of maybe she's okay.
Maybe she did just leave for some reason.
You know, some of her neighbors continued tending
to her yard and putting flowers at her door,
that kind of thing.
All of her friends really did love her.
People needed answers.
So investigators interviewed
Corey's co-worker, Leigh Locklear.
Now Leigh described Binderim's behaviour as being
erratic lately and confirmed that
he was taking cocaine again. So it added the
financial motive and also helped to understand
his character because if he was erratic, if he
was high, those things can help build a
picture towards explaining why
people do the things they do.
Leigh also told investigators a story about how one
time after taking rubbish to the local landfill,
he had joked that it would be
the perfect place to dump a body.
Now I think we're probably all guilty of that,
you know, making a joke about somewhere that
we're going to dump a body or whatever.
But in Binderim's case, this was a joke
investigators were taking very, very seriously.
He did visit the local tip straight after
visiting Susan after all.
In the hope that Binderim would divulge more
details, they set up a
conversation between him and Leigh.
In the call, Binderim told Leigh that he had been to
Home Depot in the morning before going to Susan's
house and purchased the concrete.
Leigh asked him if he still had the concrete and he
told her it had got wet in the back of his truck.
So he threw it out.
I bought two bags of concrete that
day that I went to Greg and Karen’s.
Thursday when I picked up their flooring, I
bought two sixty-five bags of concrete.
Because I told them I went to Home Depot, so I
bet they saw that I bought two bags of
concrete.
Do you still have concrete?
No, it got wet in the back of the truck. It's… yeah, I threw it out.
So this is why he went to the
tip to throw away the concrete.
But obviously it was immediately concerning
information to the investigators who needed
to find out what he had
really done with that concrete.
So investigators went to
the Rosemary Hill landfill
and obtained the check-in records
on the day of Susan's disappearance.
Now, when you go to this
landfill, your vehicle is weighed
and the scales showed that
when Binderim drove his truck
out of the facility, it was
exactly 300 pounds lighter
than when he had entered.
Now that number didn't make immediate sense when
he had told Leigh that he went to the landfill
to dump two £60 bags of concrete mix. So that
should have accounted for around about
£120 leaving an unexplained discrepancy of
£180. But that £180 soon made sickening sense.
It was very close to the
body weight of Susan Mouldin.
Investigators would later theorise that Binderim
hadn't bought those heavy bags of concrete
to use them, he bought them as a cover.
he knew the landfill weighed
every vehicle coming and going.
If he threw away a lone human body,
a sharp investigator looking at a 180 pound drop
on the receipt would instantly recognise
the weight of a person.
So by mixing Susan's body with the concrete,
Binderim believed the total numbers would
blend together on paper and disguise a murder as
nothing more than a routine trip to dump
trash.
So this man without a
doubt planned Susan's murder.
He did not go there and things got out of hand.
He knew what he was doing.
Now, unfortunately for the investigators,
Rosemary Hill was merely
a temporary holding site.
And so by the time they tracked the facility's
logistics, the rubbish from those commercial bins
had already been compacted,
loaded into massive haulage lorries,
and transported across state lines to the
Chesser Island landfill in Folkston, Georgia.
So Susan Mouldin was now somewhere inside an
active, mountain-sized landfill
that received thousands of
tons of waste every single day.
You know, needle in a haystack comes to mind,
except even a needle would
probably be easier to find, to be honest.
To search a landfill of this scale is a task so
monumental it borders the impossible.
Most law enforcement agencies will tell you that
once evidence enters a regional landfill,
it is gone forever.
but the Clay County
Sheriff's Office alongside the FBI
refused to give up on Susan.
They meticulously cross referenced the exact date
and time that Binderim
visited the transfer station
with the shipping manifests on the lorries
that left the facility and were able to isolate
the search zone to a specific area
within the Cheshire Island
landfill where she would be.
So that really helped that they could at least
kind of pinpoint an approximate area.
but it was still a massive area,
roughly the size of a baseball diamond.
I don't know what that means exactly, but it's
big anywhere from four to 25 feet
deep with rubbish buried under tons and tons of
compacted household waste that
formed towering rubbish
mountains nearly 30 feet high.
This was massive. Even isolating the area.
It was a massive area still to search.
Now luckily, having pinpointed the area, it only
contained two days of waste, including
the waste deposited on the morning Susan
disappeared, so that did help.
But it was still a lot of bloody waste, and this
is household waste, it's disgusting.
And so they went ahead
and they searched for Susan.
On the 21st of January 2020, in the dead of
winter and the freezing cold, the search began.
Every morning, dozens of searchers wearing white
protective suits, heavy boots and respirators
climbed onto the rubbish mound
and prepared for the day's work.
The process was simple but physically punishing.
Excavators broke apart the compacted section
because they couldn't physically dig into
this compacted, hardened waste.
So excavators kind of just broke it all apart.
The rubbish was then removed, bucket by bucket,
and taken to a designated working area and
spread out in thin layers known
as decks only a few inches deep.
Searchers then formed a long line and combed
through every deck with rakes, shovels and
their gloved hands,
examining each item piece by piece.
This was brutal, hard work.
The smell you can imagine was overwhelming.
Thousands of seagulls circled over heads.
The winds with that bitter steam rose
from the garbage in the early morning.
Day after day, the teams
sifted through countless decks,
finding nothing but endless
layers of household waste.
With each passing day, hope began to fade.
But then on the ninth day, a
searcher spotted something.
Buried deep within the waste,
pieces of Susan's skull had been found.
Her jawbone, bits of skull
with hair still attached.
As the search continued,
more and more remains were uncovered.
Crucially, wrapped inside the heavy-duty
plastic contractor bags,
Binderim had purchased at Home Depot,
complete with matching manufacturer barcodes.
Dental records confirmed that
the remains belonged to Susan.
An autopsy revealed that she had died from blunt
force trauma and strangulation.
Her hyoid bone had been fractured at or near
death and not after death as a result of being
crushed at the landfill.
They're really clever aren't they these people
because how the hell can you tell the difference
between a bone that's crushed before death or
afterwards in a landfill?
It's yeah that's why I don't do that job.
But there was no doubt that Susan had been
murdered and now they had a body.
They had proof.
On the 31st of January 2020, Corey Binderim, who
was already in jail being
held on separate fraud charges,
was officially arrested and
charged with Susan's murder.
We know what she did. We located
Susan. We're bringing her home.
And you're gonna be charged with murder and
tampering evidence to begin with.
I know that's a lot to hit you at
one second but obviously you've known
this whole time. You just kind
of been waiting on it I'm sure.
Not at all. I'm sure you're familiar with this
process how it goes from here.
Yeah I'm gonna tell you
I'm not gonna say anything.
You'll get upset again. No no hey hey. We won. We
got our body. You're being
Corey Binderim would be going to jail.
But thanks to the searchers who had spent nine
grueling days digging through the worst
conditions imaginable, Susan
Mouldin was finally going home.
So with the evidence finally in place,
investigators were able to
build a reconstruction of what
happened to Susan Mouldin on the morning of
Thursday 24th October 2019.
While Susan began the morning getting ready for
her day, expecting her contractor to finally
arrive with her refund, Corey Binderim pulled
up at a local Home Depot at around 704 with
a very different plan in mind.
Security cameras captured him
walking down the aisles with purpose.
He picked up two bags of quick-drying concrete
mix and a roll of
heavy-duty plastic contractor bags.
Binderim had no building work scheduled for that
day that required these materials.
After returning home for about 15 minutes,
Binderim's white pickup truck is seen pulling
into Susan's driveway at 7.48am.
Just before he gets out of his vehicle, he dials
her home landline twice.
Prosecutors would later argue this was his way of
ensuring she was awake, alone and
actively waiting for him inside.
Susan let him inside believing this nightmare was
finally coming to an end.
But instead, he confronts her.
Binderim did not have the
$12,000 to return to Susan.
He didn't even have a fraction of it.
When she refused to back down,
Binderim attacked her using his physical size
to overpower the 65-year-old widow.
Susan tried to flee, but he
pursued her through the house.
He struck her, knocking her to the ground
before ultimately strangling
her to death in her kitchen.
He then attempted to clean up the scene.
At 8:15 am, just 15
minutes after Binderim arrived.
That's when the local school bus drove down
Harbor Town Drive on its morning route
and captured Binderim's white pickup truck backed
up directly to Susan's garage door
with the tailgate dropped open.
Because inside the house Binderim was wrapping
Susan's body in heavy duty plastic sacks
he had bought just over an hour earlier.
He then lifted her into the back of his truck and
exited the house through the garage door.
37 minutes to take a life and
clean up the scene. 37 minutes.
Binderim then drove to his home at approximately
8.45am and deactivated his location sharing
app.
He changed his clothes and left again after
approximately 15 minutes.
At 9.12am Binderim drove his truck through the
gates of the Rosemary Hill Solid Waste
Management Facility and unloaded the two bags of
concrete he had purchased from Home Depot
along with Susan's body.
He left the facility at 919
and he returned to his home.
Believing he had committed the perfect crime, he
turned his phone's location sharing app
back on at 9.33am.
Binderim then drove to the
SecureCare storage facility,
arriving at his unit at 9.50
a.m. to drop off his tools.
The same ones the cadaver dogs picked up.
At 11 a.m. Binderim was captured
back on the security cameras at the home depot.
Now this trip was actually unrelated to Susan,
but what the CCTV did capture
was him wearing a different outfit,
proving he had changed his clothes
after Susan had been murdered.
At 11.25am he goes to another job but tells them
he's too sick to stay back to his old
tricks so he leaves that job.
He then returns home and basically continues with
his day as if he hadn't
just carried out a murder.
And so that is what happened to Susan.
This strong lady who was standing up for herself,
she wasn't going to be walked over.
And so he did what cowards do and took her life.
(upbeat music)
Now, although investigators
had finally uncovered the truth
of what happened to Susan,
the path to justice would be far slower.
It would take almost five years
before he ever faced a jury, five years.
Now this was because it was
2020, COVID, remember COVID.
The pandemic brought Florida's courts to a
standstill, so that didn't help.
But then there were further delays because the
state announced it would seek the death penalty.
And in capital murder cases, the wheels can turn
painfully slowly as lawyers fight over
hundreds of witnesses, endless depositions and a
mountain of legal motions.
All the legal stuff
involved delayed things further.
So October 2024, the trial of
Corey Binderim finally began.
Stepping into the courtroom,
Binderim pleaded not guilty
to the three counts charged against him,
first degree murder,
burglary with assault or battery,
and tampering with physical evidence.
Because this was a capital case,
his life was quite literally on the line.
The evidence against
Binderim was largely circumstantial
and this was not going to be an easy case
to prove to the jury.
However, the prosecution
built its case meticulously,
presenting a mountain of
physical and digital evidence.
They showed the jury the CCTV footage of Binderim
buying the concrete and the demolition bags
on the morning of the murder.
They presented the indisputable tracking data
from his mobile phone, showing his precise route
to Susan's home and then directly
to the waste transfer station.
They also introduced the
forensic pathologists findings
that despite Binderim's
attempt to hide Susan's body
in a landfill, the medical
examiner could clearly identify
that Susan had been strangled.
Over the course of the trial, 33 witnesses were
called, including Binderim's now ex-wife
Cassidy who testified that on the morning of
Susan's murder, he was seen on their ring
doorbell arriving home, backing his truck into
the garage and closing the door. Something
that she said he wasn't known
to do so it was really unusual.
Another witness called Thomas Smith was an inmate
who shared a cell block with Binderim
and he claimed Binderim had confessed to hitting
Susan and choking her to death.
Now obviously this guy's an inmate, you know, his
credibility is somewhat questionable.
But the interesting thing is that during police
interviews, he told the police that Binderim
had even said he felt something break when he
strangled Susan, matching the autopsy report
that her hyoid bone was broken.
And this makes him credible because it was
information that hadn't been released, the
police hadn't released this to anybody so if he
was telling the police that, how did
he know that? He knew that
because Binderim told him.
Now, what is anything that you tell you about
hearing anything hurt on her
broken balls, anything like that?
What did he tell you?
So you feel like something snapped.
Now the defence obviously
brought up his credibility.
He had eight felony
convictions, so I'm not surprised.
However, Smith had not
arranged a deal for his testimony.
That still doesn't mean he wasn't hoping
to get something out of it,
but his police interviews were interesting.
While the prosecution's case was strong,
the defense had a piece of forensic evidence
that was the center of their case.
And this was quite a big piece of evidence
that could potentially
show Binderim as innocent,
which is not what anybody wanted.
So two of Susan's fingernails had been found
along with the rest of
her remains at the landfill.
However, forensic testing concluded that the DNA
from the trace skin cells
on or underneath those nails
belonged to Susan, obviously they would
because they were her nails,
but also to an unknown male and not Binderim.
So the defense argued that
when someone is being strangled,
they fight back, scratching
their attacker's hands and arms
and trapping the attacker's skin cells
under their fingernails.
And I think they used the
scratch that the police saw
on Binderim to link to the idea
that if the police
thought Susan had scratched him,
then why wasn't his DNA under her nails?
But of course, we don't know
where that scratch came from.
Maybe Susan scratched him, or
maybe it was a genuine thing.
Maybe it was during his contract work.
We don't know.
So ultimately, as Binderim's
DNA was not under her nails,
the defense argued he
could not have been her killer.
And so this argument planted the seed
of reasonable doubt in the jury.
I mean at a superficial level it
does look like it clears Binderim.
I'm no forensic expert, obviously, and I don't
know which nails these were, but two
out of ten nails it's feasible that not all of
her nails would have scratched him.
And that's assuming that she did scratch him if
the autopsy showed blunt force trauma
and there was a blood spatter, she may not have
even been conscious or fully conscious
when he strangled her and so
didn't actually fight back.
Plus, as the prosecution pointed out, these nails
were found loose in the garbage.
So what this would have meant is that they would
have picked up all sorts of random environmental
DNA from all the crap from
all the surrounding waste.
So overall, the fingernail DNA evidence didn't
really help the prosecution's case.
It wasn't a helpful bit
of evidence to be in there.
The defence also tried to say that the 37 minutes
was not enough time for Binderim to
have killed Susan and cleaned the crime scene.
Well, it was.
In my non-forensic
opinion, it most definitely was.
They also argued that the evidence was largely
circumstantial and there were no direct
eyewitnesses, which there weren't.
But at the end of the day, circumstantial
evidence, when woven together
tightly, forms an unbreakable chain.
And ultimately, on Monday 14th October 2024,
after just four hours of deliberation,
the jury agreed and returned with a guilty
verdict on all three counts.
Binderim remained entirely emotionless as the
guilty verdict was read aloud.
Of course he did.
But don't forget, first degree murder is a
capital offence in Florida.
So the trial then moved into a
penalty phase a few days later
where the jury had to decide whether Binderim
should face the death penalty.
Was this man going to die for what he did to
Susan? There was no doubt he planned this.
And his motive was pure
selfishness, greed, drugs.
He was a vile man.
The prosecution argued that the crime was cold,
calculated, entirely premeditated.
It was.
The defence countered by revealing a history of
severe head trauma showing that Bindurim
had suffered multiple major concussions dating
back to his high school football days, which
they argued, along with the substance abuse, left
him struggling with impulse control.
I think they basically argued that he was
self-medicating, so he used substances to
alleviate his pain, whether physical or mental.
And so because of that, the
defense argued he didn't deserve to die.
Now, I'm not advocating for the death penalty.
I've said before, I don't agree
with it, at least in practice.
I agree with it in principle, but in practice,
too many mistakes are made.
But in principle, what the hell did Susan Mouldin
do that meant she deserved to die?
She stood her ground. She asked for the work that
she paid for. She refused to be intimidated.
That's it.
And that was a death sentence.
So it's really, really hard
to buy the defense's excuses.
But equally, as I've said many times before, the
victims in these cases are more than just
the immediate person or people affected, but
include the people around them on both sides.
Binderim had two now adult daughters.
A victim impact statement
written by them was read out,
pleading with the jury to spare his life.
Quote, "We love our father very much
and ask you to show mercy
when considering his sentence."
End quote.
This was the only time throughout the entire
trial that Binderim showed any emotion.
So under Florida's sentencing laws, a
recommendation for the death penalty requires at
least eight out of twelve
jurors to vote in favour.
When the votes were cast, the jury split seven to
five in favour of the death penalty.
He needed eight votes.
So with just one single
vote shy of the death penalty
because he got seven votes.
Binderim's life was spared.
One of the jury members later told the media that
it wasn't because they felt sorry for
Binderim but for the sake of his daughters.
And that makes sense to me, you
know, why should they suffer as well?
Just make sure his prison
sentence is, you know, difficult.
So in the end, he was sentenced to life in prison
without the possibility of parole.
He will spend the rest of his life behind bars
with no chance of ever stepping foot in free
society again. And crucially, never stepping foot
into anybody's home ever again.
[Music]
So that was the case of Susan Mouldin, a woman
who stood up for herself.
Susan didn't deserve to be thrown away like
trash. And because of her friends, she wasn't.
Their determination pulled her
out of the rubbish and got her home.
So I want to end with a testament to Susan's
friends and to friendships in general.
If you are lucky enough to have
good friends, hang on to them.
And there's one more thing.
Susan lets someone into her home
because she believed he was who he said he was.
Most of us do the same. We open our doors to
people who come to fix things,
deliver things, install things.
We don't live our lives
assuming every stranger is a threat.
But Susan's story is a
reminder that trust is a risk.
We shouldn't have to treat
everybody with suspicion.
That's no way to live.
But we do need to be aware.
To listen to our instincts, to listen to our
guts, to protect ourselves where we can.
It's a sad world when
caution becomes a necessity.
But it's an even sadder world when someone like
Susan pays the price for
trusting the wrong person.
You take good care and I will
see you back here for another
True Crime Case at my True Criminelle podcast.
Bye.